so I want to talk about the theme of
brahma vihara mm-hmm but starting with
the Jeevika Sutan madami kinda 55 okay
and just read section few sections so
the Buddha says to Jeevika Jeevika I say
that there are three instances in which
meat should not be eaten when it is seen
heard or suspected that the living being
has been slaughtered for oneself I said
that meat should not be eaten in these
three instances I say that there are
three instances in which meat may be
eaten when it is not seen not heard and
not suspected that the living being has
been floated so I say that meat may be
eaten in these three instances so it is
so the question isn't yeah if the person
who is cultivating brahma vihara
right as training in their practice or
developing or developed in their
practice can you eat meat and the
answers yes that's what he asked the
Buddha in issue well notice this Odie's
implication that's yeah so a person who
is cultivating things like kindness
compassion mudita
a banette and benevolent mind can still
eat meat so there is a way yeah so as a
lay person buying meat from a
supermarket you don't directly kill
anything right but you still you go and
you desire me to go through it you buy
it
hmm is that blameless hmm
so you know for sure the animal hasn't
been killed for you and not just that
probably that meat is not sold it's
gonna be thrown away but the same amount
of animals will be slaughtered so it
makes no difference out of water
otherwise whether you buy it or not
usually the argument is buying the meat
supposed to meet industry but that's so
far removed from any practical basis
that it's not true because if that
argument is based on that assumption
that we are all equal that we are all
the same then we all make sense at the
wheel that we could all make same
choices and that's impossible
it's impossible for all humans to make
same choices it's just inconceivable but
in theory you can conceive so in your
mind like if you stop like even if you
stop buying meat for the rest your life
and you spend every single day of your
life educating people to know buy meat
you wouldn't make a slightest dent in
the meat industry because how many
billion people are there on earth in a
way so you have to recognize the people
are different so if you want to not eat
me to not buy meat you cannot do it for
those kind of abstract projected reasons
that are not accurate you have to find
internal reasons and they are plenty to
find for like most of them then like
mass produced meat is full of hormones
and the way animals are killed needs
full of adrenaline and also to stuff but
so those should be a reason if you know
about it but if you cannot not buy it if
there is nothing else if it's the
cheapest if you like need that food it's
fine if you need it yeah but that's what
is what is the but the term is the need
but what is the blameworthy there where
is that blameless would you said it's
completely what yeah which one buying
food did you
that you could you could choose
chickpeas right right right
well it's not a moral question of
blameworthy an ongoing war it's more
like ethical question whether it's oh if
you can refrain from it don't do it with
you it's too much strain or the other
aspects of your life because the folks
are not eating in distance you need more
money and whatever else oh you can't get
any other form of protein no it's too
expensive and so on it's not optional
but as long as you are not supporting
the killing by ordering so that's I mean
it's so far removed people like again
theoretically you would think yes but we
should all act from that ideal but not
if that ideal is divorced from reality
such as people are not the same and it's
impossible to make everybody to make
same decisions it's just inconceivable
so it for a fact they will be people
they will be killing regardless if you
come across what's already killed had
nothing to do with you like oh well
should you feel guilty about taking in
it no you can if you want to but even so
it will be the guilt should be based on
ethical reason it's not a moral business
in the suit as I read further it seems
to suggest me in the theories that would
still be laying worthy to a certain
degree because of certain factors I'm
not quite sure what you're talking about
I'll read further right okay cuz a
Buddha explains what is truly blameless
right in terms of eating meat
he continued to say here at Jimmy Koenig
Ivica some bhiku lives in dependence
upon certain village of town he lives
including one section of his of his
experience within a benevolent mind
mm-hmm he has descent mm-hmm likewise
the second section of his experience the
third section the fourth so above the
lower around in everyway section of
direction Direction section of the
experience One Direction everywhere so all
One Direction everywhere so all
directions of his experience he includes
within his benevolent mind yes Walter
passed over and to all us to himself he
lives including the whole world within a
benevolent mind which is abundant
exalted immeasurable without us so he he
practices he trains that way he lives
like that mm-hmm
maybe someone who's already developed it
then a household that comes to him and
invites him for the next day's meal the
big who accepts it accepts if he likes
when the night is ended in the morning
he dresses and takes his bow and outer
robe goes to the house of that
householder and sits down on a seat made
ready then the householder serves him
with good altitude he does not think
that big who does not think how good
that the householder serves me with the
good if only a householder might serve
me with such a good arm food in the
future he does not think of us he eats
the elms food without being tied to it
infatuated with it and utterly committed
to it seeing the danger in it
understanding the escape from it what do
you think Angelica would that be coup on
such an occasion choose for his own
affliction or
and others of fiction or for the
affliction of both no Venables sir does
not that big who sustained himself with
blameless food on that occasion hmm so
that's what I'm saying that's what he's
saying is that that is the only
blameless way of potato right I see well
there's nothing to do with meat
specifically exactly yes no no I just
think because the first question was
simply about or meat non meat can you
eat it not based on what you have
available so that's like one topic but
now you talk about food in general but
as I start with that question kind of
person who at this point is it's like
you can abstain from eating meat all you
want you'll be equally blameworthy for eating
you'll be equally blameworthy for eating
with your desiring for wrong reasons
so if you and if you don't eat for wrong
reasons it's impossible for you to be
blameworthy even if you buy all the meat
in the world yeah that's what I'm saying
that's what I think it's slightly
blameworthy if you if you if you've got
a mind of design for that meat for that
taste not because you need it to mess
the only resource you have it's gonna
get there so cheapest thing yeah of
course that is blameworthy in the sense
of your designs or killing specifically
for yourself sure but once that's not
involved so you know it's not kill for
you though you know suspect they'd kill
for you and so on then your desire is
brain would but then you're not talking
about a meat anymore it's all about food
in general yeah yeah food you eat with
that desire for wrong reason not for not
for sustenance not out of the
established mind it will be blame wood
so what I find is interesting is it I
mean
the practice of that peaceful mind that
peaceful abiding benevolence is not is
what hobby scissor one dozens is not
tied to that food infatuated with idly
committed to it there's no desire for
that thing to that that household you
bring me good food to get food that is
the practice of peacefulness yeah well
practice of Metta friendliness it done
correctly establishes your mind in this
passion so there's no basis for passion
you cannot possibly exercise thoughts of
my wish she brings me this we just there
is no passion for any food any
experience because of the mind of
friendliness you're not trying to get
something fun it's inconceivable anyone
else it's impossible all you do is
protect the framework of friendliness of
an evidence of not harm because that
implies absence of passion that's why
those those states are wholesome so then
all you're not specifically sending your
meta to food you will be unable to eat
it with greed and of an end desire
because the mind is established upon
Metta properly there's no basis for any
passion triggers by the passion is
that important thing there is what you
said in the beginning when you read the
passage do you include experience within
your mind if meta you don't be in your
mind if meta towards the experience and
chase it down you recognize that this
mind of friendliness it's more general
than anything any particular person any
particular experience that can come my
way beat from North beat from South be from
beat from North beat from South be from
the West being from the East being from
up being from down so wreck recognizing
that you get to include all these
directions within your mind of
friendliness not like send your mind of
friendliness down these directions
because if you send it down north you
can't send it down east west and south
exactly it's about dealing with specific
anger or specific issues about including
any possibility for anger or issue
within the unchanging mind of
friendliness so he includes he includes
the left he includes the right the front
the back up and down he includes it all
within the framework he establishes the
right word framework first any direction
second and that's why whatever comes to
their direction
good bad neutral Pleasant food and
present food Pleasant people unpleasant
people will not perturb the mind the
feminist that's why it's called
immeasurable not tied to any particular
experience it's not fighting against
them it's overcoming the fight yet not
coveting pleasure any kind and XO comes
down a game to feelings see be able to
see if feelings well yeah yeah cuz
that's that's the measure of experience
for everyone whether experience is good
or bad is whether it's felt pleasantly
or unpleasantly and everything so by by
discerning the mind and friendliness can
remain unchanged regardless of the
pleasant or unpleasant experience
basically you're training your mind to
remain economist regardless of how I
feel I particularly feel
and that's why whether you're developing
the principle of friendliness and Metta
or principle of jhana the mind is
developed in the same way just thinking
being mindful of feelings and then
developing benevolence towards feelings
practically because the only criteria
for pleasant and pleasant agreeable
disagree it's whether how it's felt so
if you know the the unpleasant person is
unpleasant could you feel unpleasant on
account of the experience of that person
not because that unpleasantness is
contained chemically in them or
something like that and then on another
occasion when your mood is good the same
unpleasant person you don't feel
unpleasant about it if the unpleasant is
were truly in people or things it would
always be felt the same way not like the
same thing is sometimes fellow this
sometimes like that so that's what you
recognize that unpleasantness is
basically to tell you how you feel at a
time so if you train your mind to being
better verbal in regard to how you feel
at any time there's actually nothing
from any direction that can disturb that
because it's all second to it yeah well
the cultivation of peace that peace
exactly yes peace because I give me
pleasure yeah peace peace because it's
undisturbed regardless of what he says
it's peace because it's understood yeah
so that cultivating one who trains in
Bihar in the suitors
you don't hear like he trains in family
power and then he goes out to the
village to teach to do charitable work
hmm to start a garden you know teach
people how to farm how to fish okay Tim
no of course this doesn't become a
psychotherapist and you know it's the
trauma so people are management that's
all tying yourself down but when he
calls he develops brahma vihara there's
no nothing about then he goes out and
does outreach programs no he does not
know cuz it's not wiser and it says he
doesn't crave for things doesn't cover
things you just know you will that's all
that's it and that's your greatest
contribution to the world being
incapable available not spreading a lot
because that's you can you have love
without passion
can you real will without passion
impossible can you have ignorance
delusion obstinacy distraction without
passion impossible so if you remove the
passion anyone how can you hate anyone
impossible and he doesn't know that's so
the passion is a problem passion is the
root of all greed or all good and all
bad which means because of passion all good
which means because of passion all good
and bad are still tying you down
doesn't matter if it's just you know
good is better than bad but from the
ultimate point of view if you want to be
free from it all it's equally bad that's
why you would think well generosity so I
want to practice wrong with the house
actually go out and be generous but
that's just two different things
yeah generosity can help you know sort
out your circumstances you know people
will like you you crazy oh no stick we
will make
good which means practically erecting
part of the wanting to feel good now
some people who don't have any sense of
generosity they should maybe at least
two things go through the motion of
generosity just to kind of you know in
the same sense like if somebody is too
loose tightening up your restraint a bit more
tightening up your restraint a bit more
to the point of you know being a bit
painful it's a good thing but if
somebody is too tight like losing their
mind on a kind of tightness then
loosening up is good for them but it's
also to say that loosening is always
good or tightening is always good so for
somebody who is not generous who doesn't
who doesn't like even have that notion
or or any recognition of pleasantness of
sharing they should make the effort to
develop it by giving literally but it's
important to not fall into view that
giving and generosity somehow making you
closer to Nirvana
it isn't this that's the point so you
must replace bad which is non giving
stealing and so on with good but don't
mistake that replacing bad with good is
the practice of Nirvana because it isn't
you can enable you to practice navona
better but in itself it isn't so
generosity is the cosmos on the level of
virtual virtues be generous but it's not
the development of notice
it creates a basis but that basis in
itself is insufficient it's not a basis
if there is nothing placed on that basis
and so that this brahma vihara practice
and its generosity oh yeah they're two
different things yeah you don't practice
brahma vihara
by being generous you can't develop
brown without us on account of being
generous beforehand in the same sense
you can develop john on account of being
virtuous beforehand it's it's it brings
a possibility for those exact but it
doesn't automatically means you be right
inside No so drama the harvest is practice open
No so drama the harvest is practice open
upon it is practice of dispersion
practice of imperturbability practice of
remaining unaffected that's why the
ultimate that the highest browny Hara is
its opaque economic indifference so if
you practice your friendliness rightly
you will become perfectly indifferent to
everything pain and pleasure in yourself
let alone out there in the world
so the Buddha continues now Jim Jeevika
says I've heard this spindle sir
Brahma abides in benevolence compassion
contentment equanimity we met a Korean
food eater
Rebecca brandable sir the blessed one is
my visible witness to that for the
Blessed One abides in those same
qualities mm-hmm and then the Buddha
says do Buca any lust any hate any
delusion whereby ill will cruelty of
discontent or aversion might arise have
been abandoned by the targeter cut off
at the root mendler like a palm stump
done away with so that they'll no longer
subject to future rising if what you
said refer to that they're not allowed
to
that's what I mean so that is he's
surprised that's what this passion it's
not outreach programs doing this doing
this or spreading your love to the left
to the right and loving everyone no as I
said you cannot possibly love anyone
love someone and be emotionally
indifferent towards them it's a
contradiction in terms
yet the cultivation of brahma vihara is
that dispassionate emotional
imperturbable 'ti indifference and you
cannot arrive at that by spreading love
again it contradicts the very principle
of that matter you can arrive at by
practicing on hate but that's much more
subtle than just visualizing love
universal out to everyone
anyway that what do you love somebody or
not it's determined how you feel in
regard to them so if you practice
indifference toward your own feeling you
become indifferent by proxy to anyone
you love or anyone you hate and that's
how you overcome all of that yeah so
someone might you might not someone
might make you feel uncomfortable okay a
basis for you hate is that somebody
might Mike might make you feel
comfortable safe agreeable that is no
base for love and infatuation - yeah
yeah so you're saying the other day the
framework hmm but at the framework of
friendliness that's that's excelent you
know if you buy it in the qualities so
you discern the quality of friendliness
becomes the general experience or the
quality of friendliness that I dwell on
you establish your mind upon the context
of non-kill will non harm to abiding in
the quality or friendliness means
developing the context of meta and you
can only do that on the level of your
mind not on the level of chasing down
everybody you hate or don't love enough
see you make so you have to be able to
recognize those qualities yeah you know
the context of no no well I mean and
then once you decide evolve in the
context of you then you start to
recognize it doesn't matter from which
direction things come at me they all
have to converging how I feel about them
in my mind practices the context of
indifference or friendliness towards my
own feeling if your friendly towards
your own feeling you will not resist it
you will not indulge it you will not try
to get rid of it you will not try to
replace it you will be unmoved by it
so whenever something's contacting you
this is the common view is you practice
met with yourself then you spread it to
others it's true in as much you practice
method towards how you feel in regard to
anything and then you include even
experience of others within that because
there is no experience of others without
you feeling something on a kind of
experience of others so by practicing
magic correctly you only breastplates it
to yourself this is not a way and you
spread it to others by basically
including others within what you already
cultivate toward your own feeling not at
the expense of okay I finished
practicing toward myself now let me do
it towards others now that's all tied to
this and then to that and then to
thoughts and in tonight and then left
right and you have no idea but if you
develop the context correctly context
should remain unchanged regardless
whether it's you left-right north east
south doesn't matter the framework
remains of non ill will and that
framework is rooted in you being unmoved
towards whatever you cut in the feeling
good bad or neutral which are all those
things might be present so if you always
have the idea to the friend minutes
towards how you're feeling
can you experience any any thirst and
lust and passion no that implies you
want to change where you're feeling you
want more of it if you practicing
indifference toward how you're feeling
can you then act out of trying to get
rid of the unpleasantness that you might
be feeling no because I also implies you
want to change get rid of it means
you're not friendly towards it
you're not peaceful you're not peaceful
you are moved by it and you get moved by
it by acting out of it in the first
place you move yourself out of it
feelings cannot move you you move
yourself on account of what you feel
so if you break this meta friendliness
towards whatever currently feeling is
enduring you practice matters to us the
whole world because feelings are always
convergence current you cannot
experience the world without unless
through your own feelings in regard to
it impossible yeah that's how include
the world as you as you translate
initially could you just just say how
you you spread this up but the same word
can mean you include you infer you bring
it in